<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Art of Technology... Training - Ed Apps</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/ed-apps.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2015-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Minecraft for Parents</title><link href="/minecraft-for-parents.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-06-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nathan Parr</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-06-22:/minecraft-for-parents.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Useful Information about Minecraft for Parents&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h4&gt;By Nathan Parr&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Minecraft is a relatively simple game, Minecraft is difficult to describe to someone who has never played.
At its core, Minecraft is about breaking and moving cubes to gain different items and using those items to survive and build.  However, this description does not allude to the complexity of the game which is primarily limited only by your imagination.  The best way to describe the game might be to list some things you can do with it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build electronic circuits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build and play full chess games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recreate famous architecture &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a functioning computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build models of cities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaboratively build and create structures, including all kinds of buildings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore the virtual world and see new things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore dungeons and fight monsters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several different ways to play Minecraft.   There is single player mode for those who want to build and explore by themselves, as well as several different kinds multiplayer for those who would like to experience the game with their friends.  There is also survival mode for those who want a challenge and a creative mode for those who want to build without restrictions.  In Minecraft, survival mode is a little bit violent, but the intensity can be chosen by the user so you can set limits.  Other than that there is no real objectionable content in the game.
The most contentious aspect of Minecraft is, without question, servers (a server is a place where Minecraft players can play the game together from the comfort of their own homes).  Servers can be fun but they are accompanied by risks.  Those risks stem from the fact that the some servers are not operated by Mojang (the creators of Minecraft), but instead are created and operated by users.  Many of them have unmoderated text based communication.  As such the safety of a server must be assessed on a case by case basis if you feel that your child is not mature enough to choose servers responsibly and cope with any misbehavior by other players.
If your child wishes to explore collaborative play, there are several different options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The safest option is probably a LAN world (LAN is an acronym for Local Area Network which allows people connect their computers if they are close together).  A LAN world would allow your child and their friends to connect to a shared world through your home network.  This can be done through Minecraft and is almost as safe as solo play.  In addition, it is as easy as clicking a button.  The downside is that all of the computers involved need to be in the same house which limits the utility of this option. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The next safest option would be to set up a whitelist-only server using your own computer.  Only people that the admins of a server select can access one of these servers.  This would allow your child to play with any friend you approve from their own homes (explain server requirements).  There are directions online for how to do this.  And it is not as complicated as you would expect.  Your child can probably do this. There are lots of YouTube videos explaining how to do it.  It’s a great learning experience. The only risk is if your child adds someone inappropriate without your permission.  You will need at least some computer literacy to do this.  If you wish to try this, &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/url?q=http%3A%2F%2Fminecraft.gamepedia.com%2FTutorials%2FSetting_up_a_server&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;sntz=1&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNHW9VoTx8b7SmnuraGMRk-ss6e6dg"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is a guide to setting up a server, and &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/url?q=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.akliz.net%2Fmanage%2Fknowledgebase%2F5%2FHow-to-Set-Up-the-White-List-on-a-Minecraft-Server.html&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;sntz=1&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNHk1QQDCgXJ2SNLKCJWeK71aTLhhg"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is a guide to setting up the whitelist.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The final option is to allow your child to join servers set up by others.  One of their friends may have a whitelist server for which you can confirm the whitelist policy with their parents.  If that is not the case, if you feel that your child is not mature enough to safely select a server there are family-friendly servers which may be a better option.  &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/url?q=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.brightpips.com%2F11-family-friendly-minecraft-servers-where-your-kid-can-play-safely-online%2F&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;sntz=1&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNEhUDKvhBTGRI6mAHQsTwcC7XYYNg"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; page has a list of good family friendly servers and a simple, easy to understand, explanation of relevant vocabulary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Minecraft Camp" src="/images/mc-camp.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another contentious aspect of the game is modding.  Mods are modifications to Minecraft that change the game in some way.  Mods are, for the most part, relatively safe, in terms of content.  The big risk for mods is computer viruses.  This risk can be mitigated by scanning  the file multiple times with different antivirus programs.  You should check the reviews of a mod before you download it because a poorly made mod may render Minecraft incompatible. Look for well-known developers with lots of good reviews.  It’s even better if the mod is sanctioned by Mojang.  For an extra layer of protection, your child can probably confirm with friends who use the mod that they have not had any problems with it.  In addition, one should not install multiple mods at once unless it is explicitly stated that the two are compatible.  Otherwise the game will may cease to function.  Mods are not something I would recommend unless you, or someone helping to install the mod, are very computer literate.  If your child becomes an advanced user, they can even learn to code by developing their own mod.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="minecraft"></category></entry><entry><title>Tablet App - Lightbot</title><link href="/tablet-app-lightbot.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-05-22:/tablet-app-lightbot.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Long overdue praise for Lightbot&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/lightbot-programming-puzzles/id657638474?mt=8"&gt;lightbot&lt;/a&gt; while looking for apps for the &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Hour of Code&lt;/a&gt; last year. To be honest, I didn't think much of it at first -- quickly skimming through apps and preparing to lead my first class in an &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Hour of Code&lt;/a&gt;, I missed its genius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did download it and figured it would be great for the younger kids (1st and 2nd graders). And when I introduced them to it, I was correct. It was great for them. While I helped them through the first few challenges, I started to pick up on how great this app is. It quickly gets harder, yet in a very fun way. I also noticed the older kids watching and wanting to "play".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Procedures to solve recurring patterns" src="/images/lightbot.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, essentially, it is a great app for any age. It is a great "game" for people who already know how to code (like myself). The way it introduces procedures, directly relating their use in solving recurring patterns is superb. Furthermore, it exposes students to procedures, loops, conditionals and even overloading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me continue on this last point and share a couple of stories: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, I wasn't entirely thorough when introducing lightbot and mostly went through the levels with the kids as they did it. I didn't realize the impact the app was having -- students were going home and getting their parents to install it. They were using it at home and quickly surpassing my experience with the app. I didn't even know that it went into overloading until I was approached by one of my 3rd grade students who relayed to me something like, "So, instruction overloading is easy to understand, but I'm stuck on this one overloading level, can you help me?" Okay, let me just say I was speechless. Remember, I was still working on some lessons for the older kids to write code in Ruby and Python; I still viewed lightbot as a solid game to keep the younger kids happy. Now, I've got a third grader who already "gets" overloading! Clearly, I had to spend more time with this app and adjust my plans to fully leverage it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have lightbot integrated into my lessons, I can introduce concepts like overloading to kids I'm teaching to code in a programming language (like Ruby and Python). For example, when we are working through the &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Hello World, Hello &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;example, I can casually point to the "+" operator and explain that this operator is overloaded. The plus (here in Ruby) can add numbers or add strings and even add other things. First of all, overloading is not new to the lightbot kids and secondly, I hardly have to explain myself! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And its exactly these type of apps that are making my job creating lesson plans and curriculum fun and exciting. When I was in middle school teaching myself BASIC, I had to wrangle with GOSUB for weeks before I even began to understand its power. Lightbot teaches this to a 1st grader in a very interactive and visual way, builds on it, and has them "practice" it as they move through levels. Whether they know it or not, they are starting to think like a coder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I want to pass on my thanks again to the folks at &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/lightbot-inc./id657638477?mt=8"&gt;Lightbot Inc.&lt;/a&gt; who have developed &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/lightbot-programming-puzzles/id657638474?mt=8"&gt;lightbot&lt;/a&gt;. It truly is a remarkable tool for #edtech instructors. It is imperative we have as many elementary students working with procedures, loops, conditionals, and yes, overloading so that its second nature for them, so they can function in the highly tech-oriented economy in which they will live.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="apps"></category><category term="coding"></category><category term="edtech"></category></entry></feed>