<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Art of Technology... Training - Hardware</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/hardware.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2014-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Relaxation Tip: Solder</title><link href="/relaxation-tip-solder.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray Mills</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-05-21:/relaxation-tip-solder.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hyped up on coffee and stress? Go solder something.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Seems like I've always had shaky hands. Probably why I'm not a surgeon. Well, that and I didn't even opt for pre-med, or go to medical school etc. Anyway, I did my fair share of soldering during college (mostly at a camera repair shop where I worked for a couple of years). I remember then I would need to watch my coffee and sugar intake, which was hard considering our shop was a block over from spudnuts. In order to solder, I would often have to sort of meditate for a bit to calm everything down and steady the hands. Zoom ahead 20 years and I'm trying to solder again and its a mess. The harder I concentrated, the more my hands shook -- years of coffee and restless everything syndrome while coding or "software architecting" have taken their toll. Finally, I remembered the meditation technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only did this allow me to actually solder the small pieces necessary to prep student projects, but also it is healty. 1) I'm steady enough not to burn myself which is healthy and 2) this self-calming extends past the soldering session (of course now I'll start resuming normal caffeine intake to try and prove that is isn't the coffee).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, if you don't already meditate or do something similar as part of your routine, find a nice soldering project that will force you to calm your nerves. Just don't breathe any of the solder fumes!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="soldering"></category></entry></feed>