<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Art of Technology... Training - Startup</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/startup.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2017-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Read about Rockets, Pis and Alexa</title><link href="/read-about-rockets-pis-and-alexa.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-03-31T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray Mills</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-03-31:/read-about-rockets-pis-and-alexa.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Another medium post&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read about yet another cool project we'll be bringing into our classes
and camps. Check out our latest: &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-art-of-technology-training/alexa-launch-my-model-rocket-e1ebde979b34"&gt;&lt;img src="images/mission-control.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Another medium post&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read about yet another cool project we'll be bringing into our classes
and camps. Check out our latest: &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-art-of-technology-training/alexa-launch-my-model-rocket-e1ebde979b34"&gt;&lt;img src="images/mission-control.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="aws"></category><category term="alexa"></category><category term="raspberry pi"></category><category term="model rockets"></category></entry><entry><title>Read about Snakes on a Plane</title><link href="/read-about-snakes-on-a-plane.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Wray Mills</name></author><id>tag:None,2017-02-26:/read-about-snakes-on-a-plane.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;We are publishing on medium too&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And accepting submissions from all students and parents.
&lt;img alt="Python on AWS" src="images/python_lambda.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are experimenting with medium to better share and publish our
experiences running Tech Em and the great technologies we get to
use. Check out our latest &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-art-of-technology-training/python-in-the-clouds-3b0f93f61372"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on medium.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;We are publishing on medium too&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And accepting submissions from all students and parents.
&lt;img alt="Python on AWS" src="images/python_lambda.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are experimenting with medium to better share and publish our
experiences running Tech Em and the great technologies we get to
use. Check out our latest &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-art-of-technology-training/python-in-the-clouds-3b0f93f61372"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; on medium.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="aws"></category></entry><entry><title>Tech Em is a Startup run by spastically optimistic people</title><link href="/tech-em-is-a-startup-run-by-spastically-optimistic-people.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-05-30:/tech-em-is-a-startup-run-by-spastically-optimistic-people.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It helps to be spastically optimistic when launching a startup&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although Tech Em is pretty different from any other startup I've done or for which I've worked, I am getting those same sensations. Sensations of spastic optimism, often followed by lows brought on from dashed expectations. Think Bi-polar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://xerpi.com"&gt;Xerpi&lt;/a&gt; is almost 10 years old now I think and its precursor startup was the first time I had a true, large personal stake in a startup (more than just a consultant for a startup or in a senior position at a more established startup). Being so close to the startup -- completely Internet and online based where I was the IT guy (CTO title, but really a glorified coder webmaster monkey) -- I literally saw every move in my logfiles. My great friend and partner in the startup is usually very complimentary to me when it comes to running a startup. Well, except for our common spastic optimism; in fact, our typical realistic (almost cynical) attitudes about growth somehow vanish. When we get in that zone of spastic optimism, neither of us does a sanity/realistic check or even considers thinking through a worst case scenario. With a sample size of less than a dozen interactions, we would extrapolate our returns in the millions! We would spend way too much time planning how to manage the onslaught of funds and grow our business into a Google competitor (or at leat into something Google would want to buy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, its pretty easy to see how our days and weeks would go -- with expectations set as high as Google, anything short of that was a disappoinment. So, when the next 12 interactions, or worse, a few days without any interactions went by, we would be crushed. But, then the next day would bring huge results and ultimately cashflow which only fed our spastic optimism!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting Tech Em is similar, I mean, its not really a startup in as much as an startup-startdown or a 1,000 steps forward and 999.9999 steps back (in a best case scenario). I'm back on that treadmill with Tech Em. And luckily I'm really passionate about technology education and getting kids interested in science and engineering, because that makes it a lot easier to get through the startdown days. Well, that and my traditional consulting clients who have been great enough to continuing working with me as Tech Em makes these 0.001 steps/day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now with Tech Em, its all about waiting for summer camp registrations. In fact, when someone registers, that is a "VIP" email which sends an alert to my &lt;a href="http://getpebble.com"&gt;Pebble&lt;/a&gt;. When hours and days go by without that notification, the startdown is in effect. I get a notification on the Pebble and its just a news item or a text (the latter typically being a positive thing, but not usually Tech Em specific). And I'm in startdown mode up until that next registration comes and things flip back to startup mode as I try to run through all the enrollment stats again in my head -- which camps are nearing capacity? Is this a repeat family or student? How did they hear about Tech Em? What is "working" so that we can continue that and improve?! I can't wait to instruct this camp (cause, well, I have as much fun as the kids and definitely learn so much more by teaching)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, my Twitter following metric will also boost me into startup mode, so go ahead and follow &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/techemrva"&gt;us&lt;/a&gt;. And as I was amending this entry, I got a call from someone registering for a camp! That and a few new twitter followers today and I'm definitely having a startup Monday.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="startups"></category></entry></feed>