<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Art of Technology... Training - Wray</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/wray.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2015-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Gaming at TES (Fall 2015)</title><link href="/gaming-at-tes-fall-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-11-18:/gaming-at-tes-fall-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gaming ASE follow-up&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for letting Tech Em provide After School Enrichment for
your kids!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked primarily in two iOS-based apps for this class: Floors and
GamePress/Hyperpad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Floors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Floors is available for iOS (free) at &lt;a href="http://www.projectpixelpress.com"&gt;Pixel Press Floors&lt;/a&gt;.
Floors leverages "Design Thinking" -- we asked the kids
to think about the aspects of games that they like versus those that
they don't like. We actually played some games in the Floors arcade
for some comparisons before they started on their games. All students
have projects in the Floors arcade. I know some of them had better
names for there games, but in the spirit of anonymity while making
sure they can find their games, I published them in the arcade using
the techemstudios account naming them "TES-N" where N is their iPad
number (refer to your email).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GamePress&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game Press is available on iOS (free) at &lt;a href="http://www.gamepressapp.com"&gt;GamePress App&lt;/a&gt;.
GamePress is a bit more technical and uses a behavior-oriented
strategy for creating games. This is similar to apps like Scratch, but
in GamePress, the options are much more complex and students can
adjust things like the physics-related aspects of characters and
enemies. If your student worked through a GamePress App, it will be on
their thumb drive. What you'll need to do is first install
GamePress app on your iOS device and either email the .tap
file on the thumb drive to your iOS device (iPad) or AirDrop the file
to your iOS device. Your device should give you the option to open up
the file in GamePress to play the game and/or continue editing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The classic two-player tank game" src="/images/hs-talk-35.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the students preferred Floors and kept working on
their games there and some moved on with GamePress. I would certainly encourage them to keep working (or create new games) with either app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don't hesitate to comment here or email us if you have any
feedback or questions. We'd love to help these students continue
exploring software creation and learn more about Computer Science and
Software Engineering!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Floors"></category><category term="GamePress"></category><category term="Hyperpad"></category></entry><entry><title>Coding at TES (Fall 2015)</title><link href="/coding-at-tes-fall-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-11-17:/coding-at-tes-fall-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gaming ASE follow-up&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for letting Tech Em provide After School Enrichment for
your kids!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked primarily using iOS-based apps for this class. The list of
those apps is provided below along with iOS alternatives where
appropriate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lightbot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students guide a robot around 3D blocks while learning key Coding
terms and concepts. I highly encourage you to get this app for your
student and encourage them to work through the levels and read the
instructions and guidelines as they go along -- we discussed many of
them throughout the course. Go to &lt;a href="http://lightbot.com"&gt;lightbot.com&lt;/a&gt; for
more information and to get the app for Android or your desktop/laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hopscotch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on some of the concepts learned in Lightbot while adding a
few more aspects of behavior-oriented programming,
&lt;a href="http://gethopscotch.com"&gt;hopscotch&lt;/a&gt; is a terrific platform where kids truly
have fun creating their own apps and games while practicing their
coding techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pythonista&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did a little bit of coding in a text-based language, called
&lt;a href="http://python.org"&gt;python&lt;/a&gt;. This coding language is used for education and
in the Software Engineering profession. Getting started here is a
great way to continue your student's education in Computer Science and
programming that will prepare them for High School courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Floors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Floors is available for iOS (free) at &lt;a href="http://www.projectpixelpress.com"&gt;Pixel Press Floors&lt;/a&gt;.
Floors leverages "Design Thinking" -- we asked the kids
to think about the aspects of games that they like versus those that
they don't like. We actually played some games in the Floors arcade
for some comparisons before they started on their games. All students
have projects in the Floors arcade. I know some of them had better
names for there games, but in the spirit of anonymity while making
sure they can find their games, I published them in the arcade using
the techemstudios account naming them "TES-N" where N is their iPad
number (refer to your email).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don't hesitate to comment here or email us if you have any
feedback or questions. We'd love to help these students continue
exploring software creation and learn more about Computer Science and
Software Engineering!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Lightbot"></category><category term="Hopscotch"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>Minecraft Camp (August 2015)</title><link href="/minecraft-camp-august-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-08-09:/minecraft-camp-august-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;August Minecraft Camp follow-up&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some notes on the various things we did or discussed over the week. Some of the students stayed on Minecraft Pocket Edition, while most of the students worked on preparing a world for a final show-down using the PC version. Regardless, you and your students can use this blog post as a reference for doing more on your own with Minecraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minecraft PE Server&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed servers and clients and the networking involved to make games like minecraft work. We setup a minecraft PE server. If you are interested in running a PE server for your own home network, you can find one here (you must use the development version to be compatible with the latest iOS Pocket Edition):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pocketmine.net"&gt;Get PocketMine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions are relatively straightforward and this server acts similar to the PC server version in that it will create several configuration files after the first time the server is run. However, please keep in mind the following pros and cons when it comes to running this server vs. simply sharing your PE world with others on your network (essentially Minecraft PE can run as a "server" for others on your network).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine will support more players (especially if you have an i7 machine with 8+ GB ram).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine will allow op commands at the console so you have more control over your world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just like the PC edition, PocketMine has access controls (whitelist) to constrain access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just like the PC edition, PocketMine will support some plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you expose your PocketMine server to the Internet (port forward), users outside your network can join your server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine is not as stable and can get glitchy and force reconnects, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine does require a separate laptop/pc running it on the network so its not as easy to create an "ad-hoc" world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine is not quite as up-to-date as Minecraft PE and certainly behind the PC edition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href="http://www.howtogeek.com/202961/how-to-run-a-local-minecraft-pe-server-for-fun-and-persistent-world-building/"&gt;nice article&lt;/a&gt; to read with information on PocketMine and configuring it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the other thing we covered with some of the students in camp is how you can actually get another app that works with Apple's Game Center that allows you to expose your PocketMine PE world outside of your network. This is actually pretty cool, but a little tricky to setup. Furthermore, there are so many people just waiting for new PE worlds to be exposed that your world can quickly be invaded by TNT wielding and lava toting fire starters! The app's site does an ok job explaining how to set things up, but feel free to shoot me an email or comment here if you have some issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/multiplayer-for-minecraft-pe/id609704981?mt=8"&gt;Multiplayer for Minecraft PE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minecraft PE powered rails and redstone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also spent some time on minecraft PE showing how one can use powered rails and build binary logic gates! There is a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bLK58PRzaSU"&gt;good YouTube resource&lt;/a&gt; for doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't get to doing this in PC redstone, but I would encourage that you all try this at home (and let us know how it goes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="August 2015 Minecraft camp" src="/images/minecraft-camp1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minecraft Bukkit server and Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we also did quite a bit with a version of minecraft known as Bukkit. This is similar to the version that runs on the raspberry pi in that it allows us to make server modifications using Python. Here are roughly the steps we went through (and the students who coded should mostly remember how this goes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the AdventuresInMinecraft zipfile from your enrollment record (which includes some of "instructor code" that we used during the week) or download the starter kit from &lt;a href="http://blog.techemstudios.com/minecraft-camp-august-2015.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the "AdventuresInMinecraft" directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the StartBukkit command&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch Minecraft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your Minecraft profile is using version 1.6.4 (yes, bukkit is not near the latest version)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose multiplayer, direct connect, with a host of "localhost"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch the Python 2.* "IDLE" application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open up any of the modules we created in the "AdventuresInMinecraft/MyAdventures" directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The IDLE application has the option to "Run Module" which will run the python code that connects to your running bukkit server and whose results you should see in your running Minecraft application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember, building large structures (like a sphere of size 100 or greater) will take some time. Build this out of TNT and light and you will likely bog down your server for an hour or so!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your world is lagging due to some large build, you can go into "AdventuresInMinecraft/Bukkit" and delete your world! Of course, you are &lt;em&gt;deleting your world&lt;/em&gt;, so test your builds before you build in a world you want to keep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Thank you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again. I probably learned more than you all did and I appreciate that. Please comment here or send me email if you need anything else. For those of you who were using our laptops and want to do the Bukkit server on your own, let me know if you need more detailed instructions and I'll work with you all. Check out our Fall classes coming up. I know you all would do great in these classes and I'm happy to talk to you about which class would be best for your child.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="minecraft"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="bukkit"></category></entry><entry><title>WEMS Elementary Technology</title><link href="/wems-elementary-technology.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-06-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-06-04:/wems-elementary-technology.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;WEMS 2014/2015 Elementary Technology wrap-up&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;WEMS Elementary Technology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had a really great time teaching Technology to the WEMS Elementary students! They have been such a terrific and patient class this year as we reviewed things as complex as Binary Logic gates, the binary number system, and even the hexadecimal number system. I truly enjoy instructing in the Montessori environment as they are so open to new concepts and can help me relate them to their other subjects. And the older students are able to help the younger students in a way that reinforces everyone's understanding. I especially appreciate their patience because we steered away from the afternoon iPad sessions and stuck to a more traditional lecture/show-and-tell approach -- they did some iPad technology work on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the recurring request by the students for me to bring them transistors, they now each have their very own (PNP) transistor and an LED! Again, I am so pleased with their enthusiasm and now understanding of how transistors (used to implement switching/digital logic) are the basic building blocks for the digital devices we all own and carry around today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for those students who actually want to build something with their transistor and LED, you can go to &lt;a href="http://www.adafruit.com"&gt;adafruit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://amazon.com"&gt;amazon&lt;/a&gt; (specific links to items coming) to order a few additional items to build a simple switching circuit and even a NOT gate (ask your child to explain a not gate -- hopefully they'll remember what a truth table is and show you the truth table for AND, OR, and NOT). To get started with their transistor and LED, they should probably get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prototyping breadboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9V wire and battery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;550 Ohm resistors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;push button switch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pack of jumper wires&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to order more switches, transistors and leds. You may want to see if the remaining Richmond Radio Shack stores still have some electronics project starter kits which include many of these things in one nice bundle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then build this simple circuit whereby pressing the button turns on the transistor which turns on the "main" circuit to turn on the LED. Note the position of the transistor -- the flat side is facing down in the pictures (which lines the three leads to the transistor to be in the order of emitter, base, and collector). Your child may remember earlier in the year when we had several of them pretend to be a transistor and we had one student providing power, one student controlling, and another student as the LED -- the controlling student was "wired" to the base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Simple switching circuit -- off" src="/images/simple-off.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Simple switching circuit -- off" src="/images/simple-off2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Simple switching circuit -- on" src="/images/simple-on.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, your child should enjoy this simple wiring change that allows the transistor to stop the "main" circuit. That is, pressing the button will turn off the LED -- essentially creating the NOT logic. The light is on unless the button is pressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Not gate -- off" src="/images/not-off.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Not gate -- off" src="/images/not-off2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Not gate -- on" src="/images/not-on.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to comment here or send me an email wray(at)techemstudios.com .&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="edtech"></category><category term="transistors"></category><category term="leds"></category><category term="binary"></category></entry><entry><title>Gaming at TES (Winter 2015)</title><link href="/gaming-at-tes-winter-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-03-25:/gaming-at-tes-winter-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gaming ASE follow-up&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for letting Tech Em provide After School Enrichment for
your kids! This was a terrific group -- very focused and pretty quiet
considering they were mostly working on and playing games! Well, that
is until they found out they could play iTunes radio on their iPads
the last day!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We worked primarily in two iOS-based apps for this class: Floors and
GamePress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Floors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Floors is available for iOS (free) at &lt;a href="http://www.projectpixelpress.com"&gt;Pixel Press Floors&lt;/a&gt;.
Floors leverages "Design Thinking" -- we asked the kids
to think about the aspects of games that they like versus those that
they don't like. We actually played some games in the Floors arcade
for some comparisons before they started on their games. All students
have projects in the Floors arcade. I know some of them had better
names for there games, but in the spirit of anonymity while making
sure they can find their games, I published them in the arcade using
the techemstudios account naming them "TES-N" where N is their iPad
number (refer to your email).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GamePress&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game Press is available on iOS (free) at &lt;a href="http://www.gamepressapp.com"&gt;GamePress App&lt;/a&gt;.
GamePress is a bit more technical and uses a behavior-oriented
strategy for creating games. This is similar to apps like Scratch, but
in GamePress, the options are much more complex and students can
adjust things like the physics-related aspects of characters and
enemies. If your student worked through a GamePress App, it will be on
their thumb drive. What you'll need to do is first install
GamePress app on your iOS device and either email the .tap
file on the thumb drive to your iOS device (iPad) or AirDrop the file
to your iOS device. Your device should give you the option to open up
the file in GamePress to play the game and/or continue editing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The classic two-player tank game" src="/images/hs-talk-35.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the students preferred Floors and kept working on
their games there and some moved on with GamePress. I would certainly encourage them to keep working (or create new games) with either app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don't hesitate to comment here or email us if you have any
feedback or questions. We'd love to help these students continue
exploring software creation and learn more about Computer Science and
Software Engineering!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Floors"></category><category term="GamePress"></category></entry><entry><title>Homeschool Conference (201503)</title><link href="/homeschool-conference-201503.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-03-24:/homeschool-conference-201503.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Highlights from my presentation&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since I covered a bunch of stuff, here are some of the references
and high points from my talk: "Technology in your Homeschool Curriculum"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Homeschool Student working on code for microcontroller" src="/images/hs-talk-40.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/circuit-coder/id492180472"&gt;Circuit Coder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://lightbot.com"&gt;Lightbot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://scratch.mit.edu"&gt;Scratch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gethopscotch.com"&gt;Hopscotch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://omz-software.com/pythonista/"&gt;Pythonista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.gamepressapp.com"&gt;GamePress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.projectpixelpress.com/floors/"&gt;Floors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.adafruit.com"&gt;Adafruit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org"&gt;RaspberryPi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prehistoric: Tally Sticks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1800's, mechanical: Pascal's Calculator, Arithmometer, Babbage's&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machines, Ada Lovelace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1940's, vacuum tube: ENIAC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1970' to today: microchip and the raspberry pi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;ENIAC vs. Raspberry Pi&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ENIAC vs. Raspberry Pi" src="/images/hs-talk-11.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Binary Logic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can one do with billions of transistors?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with one transistor, simple switching device (digital). It's on
or off, true or false, 0 or 1. Wire a couple together and you get an
AND gate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="AND Gate" src="/images/hs-talk-15.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combine a NOT gate and an AND gate and you can solve the
truth table where you want the output to be true (1) only when B
is 1. That is to say: let there be truth when (NOT A) AND B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="&amp;quot;Quarter&amp;quot; Adder" src="/images/hs-talk-18.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you wire the A input to a NOT gate and have that go into an AND gate that
B is also wired to, then you have the result. Suppose you now want to add A
and B, then simply use the mirror of (NOT A) AND B and "OR" it: ((NOT A)
AND B) OR (A AND (NOT B)). That gives you the sum, but don't forget
the carry which is simply A AND B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Half adder truth table" src="/images/hs-talk-19.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Half adder circuit" src="/images/hs-talk-21.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Half adder running circuit" src="/images/hs-talk-22.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you have a binary half adder (you can add two digits). Combine two
of those (along with an OR of the CARRY output for each) and you have
a full adder. String together 3 full adders and you can add two 3
digit binary numbers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Binary addition" src="/images/hs-talk-27.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Binary adder circuit" src="/images/hs-talk-28.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Binary adder running circuit" src="/images/hs-talk-29.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wasn't that easy??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Coding&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having gone through lightbot, a teacher can re-iterate the
fundamentals with a language like Python: procedures, overloading,
loops, and conditionals. Futhermore, with concepts learned in Scratch,
Hopscotch, and even game-creation apps like GamePress, variables of
varying data-types can be explained. Start with a simple program to
emulate "Mad Libs" and work up to more complex programs that can
leverage device (pythonista) libraries for accelerometer or screen
input; leverage minecraft (Bukkit server) libraries to build things in
a Minecraft world; leverage GPIO libraries to read sensor input/update
led output from a raspberry pi cobbler kit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Make it... Fun" src="/images/hs-talk-46.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This BMO-creeper contains a student coded microcontroller, not TNT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="BMO-Creeper" src="/images/hs-talk-41.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="computer science"></category><category term="binary"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="raspberry pi"></category><category term="adafruit"></category><category term="gemma"></category><category term="lightbot"></category></entry><entry><title>Craft of Minecraft (Winter 2015)</title><link href="/craft-of-minecraft-winter-2015.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-03-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-03-16:/craft-of-minecraft-winter-2015.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The promised blog page that goes along with the winter Craft of Minecraft&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;Minecraft PE Server&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started the class discussing servers and clients and the networking involved to make games like minecraft work. We setup a minecraft PE server (that is actually still running). If you are interested in running a PE server for your own home network, you can find a fairly stable version here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pocketmine.net"&gt;Get PocketMine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions are relatively straightforward and this server acts similar to the PC server version in that it will create several configuration files after the first time the server is run. However, please keep in mind the following pros and cons when it comes to running this server vs. simply sharing your PE world with others on your network (essentially Minecraft PE can run as a "server" for others on your network).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine will support more players (especially if you have an i7 machine with 8+ GB ram).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine will allow op commands at the console so you have more control over your world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just like the PC edition, PocketMine has access controls (whitelist) to constrain access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just like the PC edition, PocketMine will support some plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you expose your PocketMine server to the Internet (port forward), users outside your network can join your server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine is not as stable and can get glitchy and force reconnects, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine does require a separate laptop/pc running it on the network so its not as easy to create an "ad-hoc" world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PocketMine is not quite as up-to-date as Minecraft PE and certainly behind the PC edition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href="http://www.howtogeek.com/202961/how-to-run-a-local-minecraft-pe-server-for-fun-and-persistent-world-building/"&gt;nice article&lt;/a&gt; to read with information on PocketMine and configuring it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the other thing we covered in class is how you can actually get another app that works with Apple's Game Center that allows you to expose your PocketMine PE world outside of your network. This is actually pretty cool, but a little tricky to setup. Furthermore, there are so many people just waiting for new PE worlds to be exposed that your world can quickly be invaded by TNT wielding and lava toting fire starters! The app's site does an ok job explaining how to set things up, but feel free to shoot me an email or comment here if you have some issues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/multiplayer-for-minecraft-pe/id609704981?mt=8"&gt;Multiplayer for Minecraft PE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minecraft PE powered rails and redstone&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also spent some time on minecraft PE showing how one can use powered rails and build binary logic gates! There is a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bLK58PRzaSU"&gt;good YouTube resource&lt;/a&gt; for doing that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't get to doing this in PC redstone, but I would encourage that you all try this at home (and let us know how it goes). In fact, once we move our newer server (and the world they played in the last day), it would be awesome if some of the students could build some logic gates in that world to share with other students. We will definitely give them credit for providing instructional materials!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Winter 2015 Minecraft class" src="/images/minecraft-class1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Minecraft Bukkit server and Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we also did quite a bit with a version of minecraft known as Bukkit. This is the same version that runs on the raspberry pi and it worked well for the group we had in our class -- allowing us to make server modifications using Python. Here are roughly the steps we went through (and the students should mostly remember how this goes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the "AdventuresInMinecraft" directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the StartBukkit command&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch Minecraft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your Minecraft profile is using version 1.6.4 (yes, bukkit is not near the latest version)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose multiplayer, direct connect, with a host of "localhost"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch the Python 2.* "IDLE" application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open up any of the modules we created in the "AdventuresInMinecraft/MyAdventures" directory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The IDLE application has the option to "Run Module" which will run the python code that connects to your running bukkit server and whose results you should see in your running Minecraft application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember, building large structures (like a sphere of size 100 or greater) will take some time. Build this out of TNT and light and you will likely bog down your server for an hour or so!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your world is lagging due to some large build, you can go into "AdventuresInMinecraft/Bukkit" and delete your world! Of course, you are &lt;em&gt;deleting your world&lt;/em&gt;, so test your builds before you build in a world you want to keep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Winter 2015 Minecraft class" src="/images/minecraft-class2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Thank you&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again. I probably learned more than you all did and I appreciate that. Please comment here or send me email if you need anything else. For those of you who were using our laptops and want to do the Bukkit server on your own, let me know if you need more detailed instructions and I'll work with you all. Check out our Spring session and Summer Camps coming up. We are combining raspberry pi and minecraft for some fun projects -- I know you all would do great in these classes and I'm happy to talk to you in advance if you have specific objectives in mind for your next minecraft/pi projects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="minecraft"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="bukkit"></category></entry><entry><title>Student LED-faced Robots (aka BMO)</title><link href="/student-led-faced-robots-aka-bmo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-06-05:/student-led-faced-robots-aka-bmo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some of the student design LEDs&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of the Homeschool courses and an Elementary enrichment course, we ended up making 23 LED-faced robots. That means there are 23 #rva kids who came up with their own set of LED "frames" design, coded it, and programmed their bot's microcontroller. Here are pics of some of some early prototypes followed by finished projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Initial prototype" src="http://photos-f.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xpa1/10326632_305850922903469_1379628513_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code sketch test rig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Code sketch test rig" src="http://scontent-b.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xfa1/t51.2885-15/10251544_310116335803865_818320578_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From graph paper to code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Coding" src="http://photos-d.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xfp1/10299889_480754238692379_1525559746_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L's robot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="L's robot" src="http://photos-a.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xpa1/10296722_602473726514704_1077854084_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O's robot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="O's robot" src="http://scontent-a.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xfp1/t51.2885-15/10413939_251208148409562_1082851062_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M's robot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="M's robot" src="http://photos-h.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xpf1/10375690_652704118150967_1990901006_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="edtech"></category><category term="led"></category><category term="gemma"></category></entry><entry><title>Tech Em is a Startup run by spastically optimistic people</title><link href="/tech-em-is-a-startup-run-by-spastically-optimistic-people.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-05-30:/tech-em-is-a-startup-run-by-spastically-optimistic-people.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It helps to be spastically optimistic when launching a startup&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although Tech Em is pretty different from any other startup I've done or for which I've worked, I am getting those same sensations. Sensations of spastic optimism, often followed by lows brought on from dashed expectations. Think Bi-polar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://xerpi.com"&gt;Xerpi&lt;/a&gt; is almost 10 years old now I think and its precursor startup was the first time I had a true, large personal stake in a startup (more than just a consultant for a startup or in a senior position at a more established startup). Being so close to the startup -- completely Internet and online based where I was the IT guy (CTO title, but really a glorified coder webmaster monkey) -- I literally saw every move in my logfiles. My great friend and partner in the startup is usually very complimentary to me when it comes to running a startup. Well, except for our common spastic optimism; in fact, our typical realistic (almost cynical) attitudes about growth somehow vanish. When we get in that zone of spastic optimism, neither of us does a sanity/realistic check or even considers thinking through a worst case scenario. With a sample size of less than a dozen interactions, we would extrapolate our returns in the millions! We would spend way too much time planning how to manage the onslaught of funds and grow our business into a Google competitor (or at leat into something Google would want to buy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, its pretty easy to see how our days and weeks would go -- with expectations set as high as Google, anything short of that was a disappoinment. So, when the next 12 interactions, or worse, a few days without any interactions went by, we would be crushed. But, then the next day would bring huge results and ultimately cashflow which only fed our spastic optimism!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting Tech Em is similar, I mean, its not really a startup in as much as an startup-startdown or a 1,000 steps forward and 999.9999 steps back (in a best case scenario). I'm back on that treadmill with Tech Em. And luckily I'm really passionate about technology education and getting kids interested in science and engineering, because that makes it a lot easier to get through the startdown days. Well, that and my traditional consulting clients who have been great enough to continuing working with me as Tech Em makes these 0.001 steps/day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now with Tech Em, its all about waiting for summer camp registrations. In fact, when someone registers, that is a "VIP" email which sends an alert to my &lt;a href="http://getpebble.com"&gt;Pebble&lt;/a&gt;. When hours and days go by without that notification, the startdown is in effect. I get a notification on the Pebble and its just a news item or a text (the latter typically being a positive thing, but not usually Tech Em specific). And I'm in startdown mode up until that next registration comes and things flip back to startup mode as I try to run through all the enrollment stats again in my head -- which camps are nearing capacity? Is this a repeat family or student? How did they hear about Tech Em? What is "working" so that we can continue that and improve?! I can't wait to instruct this camp (cause, well, I have as much fun as the kids and definitely learn so much more by teaching)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, my Twitter following metric will also boost me into startup mode, so go ahead and follow &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/techemrva"&gt;us&lt;/a&gt;. And as I was amending this entry, I got a call from someone registering for a camp! That and a few new twitter followers today and I'm definitely having a startup Monday.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="startups"></category></entry><entry><title>Tablet App - Lightbot</title><link href="/tablet-app-lightbot.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2014-05-22T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Wray</name></author><id>tag:None,2014-05-22:/tablet-app-lightbot.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Long overdue praise for Lightbot&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/lightbot-programming-puzzles/id657638474?mt=8"&gt;lightbot&lt;/a&gt; while looking for apps for the &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Hour of Code&lt;/a&gt; last year. To be honest, I didn't think much of it at first -- quickly skimming through apps and preparing to lead my first class in an &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Hour of Code&lt;/a&gt;, I missed its genius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did download it and figured it would be great for the younger kids (1st and 2nd graders). And when I introduced them to it, I was correct. It was great for them. While I helped them through the first few challenges, I started to pick up on how great this app is. It quickly gets harder, yet in a very fun way. I also noticed the older kids watching and wanting to "play".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Procedures to solve recurring patterns" src="/images/lightbot.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, essentially, it is a great app for any age. It is a great "game" for people who already know how to code (like myself). The way it introduces procedures, directly relating their use in solving recurring patterns is superb. Furthermore, it exposes students to procedures, loops, conditionals and even overloading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me continue on this last point and share a couple of stories: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said, I wasn't entirely thorough when introducing lightbot and mostly went through the levels with the kids as they did it. I didn't realize the impact the app was having -- students were going home and getting their parents to install it. They were using it at home and quickly surpassing my experience with the app. I didn't even know that it went into overloading until I was approached by one of my 3rd grade students who relayed to me something like, "So, instruction overloading is easy to understand, but I'm stuck on this one overloading level, can you help me?" Okay, let me just say I was speechless. Remember, I was still working on some lessons for the older kids to write code in Ruby and Python; I still viewed lightbot as a solid game to keep the younger kids happy. Now, I've got a third grader who already "gets" overloading! Clearly, I had to spend more time with this app and adjust my plans to fully leverage it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have lightbot integrated into my lessons, I can introduce concepts like overloading to kids I'm teaching to code in a programming language (like Ruby and Python). For example, when we are working through the &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Hello World, Hello &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;example, I can casually point to the "+" operator and explain that this operator is overloaded. The plus (here in Ruby) can add numbers or add strings and even add other things. First of all, overloading is not new to the lightbot kids and secondly, I hardly have to explain myself! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And its exactly these type of apps that are making my job creating lesson plans and curriculum fun and exciting. When I was in middle school teaching myself BASIC, I had to wrangle with GOSUB for weeks before I even began to understand its power. Lightbot teaches this to a 1st grader in a very interactive and visual way, builds on it, and has them "practice" it as they move through levels. Whether they know it or not, they are starting to think like a coder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I want to pass on my thanks again to the folks at &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/artist/lightbot-inc./id657638477?mt=8"&gt;Lightbot Inc.&lt;/a&gt; who have developed &lt;a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/lightbot-programming-puzzles/id657638474?mt=8"&gt;lightbot&lt;/a&gt;. It truly is a remarkable tool for #edtech instructors. It is imperative we have as many elementary students working with procedures, loops, conditionals, and yes, overloading so that its second nature for them, so they can function in the highly tech-oriented economy in which they will live.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="apps"></category><category term="coding"></category><category term="edtech"></category></entry></feed>